Songlin Jiang

✓ songlin.jiang@aalto.fi
 ♦ hollowman6.github.io
 • in songlin-jiang
 ✓ HollowM186
 • Q HollowMan6
 • Last updated on November 11, 2023

My academic fervor converges with enhancing **computer systems**, **networks**, **databases**, and their corresponding **security** aspects, which allows my research to have impacts on computing for both the environment (**greener while efficient**) and people (**faster while reliable**). Additionally, I am a passionate **free software advocate**. During my leisure time, I maintain several open-source projects and contribute to many others.

Education

M.Sc. in SECCLO Erasmus Mundus, Aalto University (4.93/5)

2022 - 2024

- Specialization: Security and Cloud Computing
- O Thesis: Real-time GPU Usage Alert Service for Jobs on Pre-exascale HPC Clusters
- O Supervisor: Prof. Bo Zhao

M.Sc. in SECCLO Erasmus Mundus, Technical University of Denmark (DTU)

2023 - 2024

- Specialization: Reliable Distributed Systems
- Thesis: Real-time GPU Usage Alert Service for Jobs on Pre-exascale HPC Clusters
- O Supervisor: Prof. Bernd Dammann

Exchange, University of Leeds

Spring 2020

B.Eng. in Computer Science & Technology (Honors), Lanzhou University (91/100)

2018 - 2022

- Thesis: A Short-Term Wind Speed Multistep-Ahead Hybrid Prediction Model based on ICEEMDAN and Prophet-GRU-NN
- O Supervisor: Prof. Chao Ren

Experience

HPC Develop Thesis Worker, CSC - IT Center for Science

01/2024 - 07/2024

- \odot Work on my master's thesis for SECCLO Erasmus Mundus program
- o Implement the real-time GPU usage alert service for HPC clusters
- Investigate the continuous aggregates feature of TimescaleDB
- LUMI ranked 3rd around the world and 1st in Europe at HPC supercomputer TOP500 list by 2023

Developer Relations Engineer, Enclaive (confidential computing, with Prof. Sebastian Gajek) 06/2023 - Present

- O Create technical documentation, tutorials and content
- Manage channel to interact with the community and grow the customer base

Coding Experience, Igalia (Wolvic, ex. Mozilla Firefox Reality)

06/2023 - Present

- O Develop VR Browser, refactor Android deprecated methods
- O Address user issues. Implement UI, browser, and openXR related features
- o Contribute to the majority of the features available from v1.4.2, v1.5, and v1.5.1

HPC Developer Internship, CSC - IT Center for Science

05/2023 - 08/2023

- O Develop the **GPU monitoring service** for HPC clusters (NVIDIA and AMD GPUs, including LUMI)
- O Develop the Documentation GPT chatbot service using IlamaIndex, LangChain and Redis
- Make improvements to the HPC web operating interface project Open OnDemand using Ruby on Rails

CNCF LFX Mentorship, *Kubescape* (Kubernetes security platform) 03/2023 - 05/2023O Add packaging support for various package managers in Linux, macOS, and Windows Improve release CI by adding ARM64 binaries building and testing support (QEMU and cross compiling) Add support for Kubescape auto version bumping in other Kubescape-related repositories Enable Kubescape GitHub action to support code review based on generated SARIF report O A blog post by Cloud Native Computing Foundation (CNCF) that introduces my work Rhino-Bird Open-Source Training Program, Tencent (Kona JDK) 07/2022 - 09/2022 Investigate keypairs generation for SM2 with JDK, compare performance and security of algorithms Google Summer of Code, MIT CSAIL & Google (Blockly, web-based visual program editor) 05/2022 - 09/2022 Create a plugin to allow selecting, dragging and manipulating multiple blocks at once for Google Blockly O Resolve the issue that had troubled the **Google Engineers** for a **decade** (since the Blockly project started) @mit-app-inventor/blockly-plugin-workspace-multiselect now has average 50+ downloads per week **Summer of Bitcoin**, *Cryptoanarchy Debian* (Bitcoin related Debian packages) 05/2022 - 08/2022 Add Continuous Integration (CI) by investigating systemd support inside Docker with GitHub Actions • The chance to get into this internship in 2022: 83/20317 RL Open Source Fest, Microsoft Research NYC (Vowpal Wabbit, ML library) 05/2022 - 08/2022 Add native CSV parser support for the Vowpal Wabbit project in C++, 100% Test & Code Coverage O Manage to make 10x performance improvement and is comparable to speed of original VW text format Open Source Intern, Institute of Software, CAS (openEuler, Linux distribution) 01/2022 - 07/2022o First to obtain 150 intern credits. Help solve 6 issues, related technologies include D-Bus, Glib, building Cloud Native Container images, Rust programming, Chrome DevTools Protocol, test case, RPM packaging One of the achievements mdbook-pdf now has average 100+ downloads per week **Google Summer of Code**, *openSUSE* (IBus, input method framework) 06/2021 - 08/2021 Add customizing themes feature for IBus in desktop environments, improve IBus settings support in GNOME O A blog post at **openSUSE News** that introduces my work GNOME extension Customize IBus now has average 100+ downloads per week **OSPP Summer**, *openEuler* (Developed an ISO writer using QT and C++) 07/2021 - 09/2021**OSPP Summer**, *Emacs Application Framework* (EAF, work with Yong Wang) 07/2020 - 09/2020 Add new features and address all kinds of issues using Emacs Lisp, Python, JavaScript, SQLite A blog post (in Chinese) about my work posted by Yong Wang (ManateeLazyCat) **Summer of Code**, *Alibaba* (Arthas, Java diagnostic tool) 07/2020 - 08/2020 Create Chinese and English interactive online tutorials for Arthas using Katacoda and Vue.js Coding part highlight: Support directly searching Class Loader by name instead of Hash Code in Java O A Wechat post (in Chinese) about my work posted by hengyunabc Certificates & Honors & Awards

SECCLO Erasmus Mundus Scholarship

2022 - 2024

(26/767) Full-ride scholarship, includes full tuition fee waiver, covers all living costs and travel expenses

Aalto University School of Science Dean's Incentive Scholarship

2023

Cloud Captains in Linux Foundation Training (LiFT) Scholarship (China)	2022
Huawei Cloud Certified Developer Associate in Internet of Things (HCCDA - IoT)	2022
Certified Kubernetes Administrator (CKA), CNCF	2022
Recognized Tencent Open Source Contributor	2022
Only 30+ were issued globally by the end of 2022 Intern of Excellence Award at Tencent	2022
Only 2/4000+ received all the 3 kinds of intern awards Intern of Excellence & Star of Open Source Award in openEuler Open Source Internship	2022
Only 3/150+ interns received both awards China Ministry of Education & Huawei "Intelligent Base" Future Star Scholarship	2021
Software Design Engineer, China Qualification of Computer and Software Professional	2021
Excellent Student Award in Baidu Software Engineering Training Camp	2021
Academic Aces in Linux Foundation Training (LiFT) Scholarship (China)	2020
CATTI Level 3 (English & Chinese) Translator	2020
Best Paper Award in Lanzhou University Summer Social Practice Report	2020
Paper: Research on the Functionality and Optimization of Urban Communities in China During COVID-19 in 2020 Award in openEuler University Developer Competition	2020
(24/547 Teams) I participated alone, ranked 1st in final defense Star of Innovation Award in Alibaba T-head OCC Developers IoT Innovation Competition	2020
My proposal ranked 1st in voting (850 votes, 300 more than the 2nd one) China Scholarship Council Outstanding Undergraduate International Exchange Scholarship	2019
(Only 1) Full covering of visa fees, traveling fees, and living costs, plus the host university exchange program tuition fee we Google InnoCamp Hangzhou BoostMakers — TensorFlow Boost	vaiver agreement 2019
Only 40+/2000+ got this certificate Excellent Project Award in Lanzhou University Innovation and Entrepreneurship Plan	2019
Project: Renaissance – AI + Dunhuang Art, supervised by Prof. Qingguo Zhou Nine Lanzhou University undergraduate scholarships	2018 – 2022
$3 \times \text{scholarship for academic excellence, } 5 \times \text{scholarship for innovation and entrepreneurship projects, } 2020 \text{ scholarship for } 100 \times 100 \times$	IELTS test fee

Open Source Repositories

1.5k+ GitHub followers. 55.6k+ GitHub stars across all of the following selected repositories:

1.	kubescape/kubescape	★ 9.1k	Kubernetes Security Platform	2023
2.	Rank $\#9$ among all contributors with 40 commits, 745 lines of add $Igalia/wolvic$		555 lines of deletions Immersive VR Browser	2023
3.	Rank $\#7$ among all contributors with 117 commits, 8008 lines of a VowpalWabbit/vowpal_wabbit		d 3712 lines of deletions Machine Learning System	2022
4.	Rank $\#77$ among all contributors with 3 commits, 1611 lines of ad ThibaultJanBeyer/DragSelect		83 lines of deletions Multi-Select UI Library	2022
5.	Rank #6 among all contributors with 3 commits, 213 lines of addit debian-cryptoanarchy/cryptoanarchy-deb-repo-builded	er ★ 138	Bitcoin Packages for Debian	2022
	Rank #4 among all contributors with 7 commits, 245 lines of additional additional and the contributors with 7 commits, 245 lines of additional	tions and 2	2 lines of deletions	

6. HollowMan6/mdbook-pdf	★ 106	MdBook backend for PDF Generatio	n 2022
Rank $\#1$ among all contributors with 35 commits, 3152 lines of	f additions and	527 lines of deletions	
7. mit-cml/workspace-multiselect	★ 5	Blockly Multi-Select Plugin	2022
Rank $\#1$ among all contributors with 18 commits, 11846 lines of	of additions an	d 20978 lines of deletions	
8. openSUSE/Customize-IBus	★ 47	Full Customization of IBus UI	2021
Rank $\#1$ among all contributors with 354 commits, 42984 lines	of additions a	nd 30128 lines of deletions	
9. HollowMan6/Wechat-Timed-Message	★ 22	GitHub action for WeChat Message	2021
Rank $\#1$ among all contributors with 99 commits, 4139 lines of	f additions and	1718 lines of deletions	
10. openSUSE/IBus-Theme-Hub	★ 19	IBus Themes CSS Hub	2021
Rank $\#1$ among all contributors with 21 commits, 3190 lines of	f additions and	442 lines of deletions	
11. openSUSE/IBus-Theme-Tools	★ 13	IBus Theme Generator	2021
Rank $\#1$ among all contributors with 104 commits, 8558 lines	of additions an	d 4654 lines of deletions	
12. alibaba/arthas	★ 33.7k	Java Diagnostic Tool	2020
Rank $\#2$ among all contributors with 80 commits, 25191 lines	of additions an	d 1543 lines of deletions	
13. emacs-eaf/emacs-application-framework	★ 2.8k	Emacs Application Framework	2020
Rank #5 among all contributors with 49 commits, 3482 lines of	f additions and	1033 lines of deletions	
14. HollowMan6/TinyML-ESP32	★ 106	TinyML Programs for ESP32	2020
Rank $\#1$ among all contributors with 11 commits, 78393 lines	of additions an	d 19530 lines of deletions	
15. HollowMan6/SRMD-Pytorch	★ 20	Super Resolution Model	2020
Rank $\#1$ among all contributors with 23 commits, 21397 lines	of additions an	d 1399 lines of deletions	

Invited Talks

Content, Link to the talk, and Date:

1. Virtual Network Systems among Containers, Aalto University Secure Systems Demo Day	06/2023
2. Multi-Select Plugin, Google Blockly Summit	06/2023
3. Native CSV Parser, Microsoft Research NYC Seminar (RLOSFest)	08/2022
4. Summary of my Open Source Internship, openEuler Excellent Intern Seminar	08/2022
5. Update Notification Program in Python, openEuler University Developer Competition	05/2021
6. Summary of my Contribution to Arthas, Alibaba Summer of Code Presentation	08/2020

Professional Activities

Main...openSUSE Member 2021 – Present

Spen303L Member 2021 – Fresen

 $Continued \ and \ substantial \ contributions \ to \ the \ open SUSE \ project. \ With \ voting \ rights \ and \ the \ ability \ to \ run \ for \ the \ open SUSE \ board$

Reviewing.....

O SIGMOD 2023 Reproducibility Evaluation Reviewer

Software Copyright

 Hollow Software for Smartly Memorizing Words 	CN 2020SR0839716
 Hollow Software System for Sport Center Management 	CN 2020SR0839709
 Hollow Software for Jack Compiler 	CN 2020SR0839702
O Hollow Software for Picture & Video Information Hiding En-Decryption	CN 2020SR0079950
Face Recognition Access Control System	CN 2019SR1388115

Publications [Google Scholar, 2 citations with h-index of 1]

2019.....

1. Voting System Based on Wechat Pay Songlin Jiang

Computer Engineering & Software 2019

Skills

Programming C++, Go, Rust, Python, C, Java, Kotlin, JavaScript, SQL, HTML, Bash, PHP, Ruby ...
 Frameworks Docker, TensorFlow, PyTorch, Pandas, Numpy, GitHub Actions, Flutter, React, QT ...
 DataBases PostgreSQL, MongoDB, Redis, InfluxDB, TimescaleDB, HBase, Hive, Hadoop, Spark ...

Courses

Some top-quality courses I've taken:

○ Program Analysis, DTU	Fall 2023
○ Program Verification, DTU	Fall 2023
 Programming Parallel Computers, Aalto University 	Spring 2023
O Platform Security, Aalto University	Spring 2023
 Cloud Software and Systems, Aalto University 	Fall 2022
 Multimedia Services in Internet, Aalto University 	Fall 2022
O Designing and Building Scalable Web Applications, Aalto University	Fall 2022
Network Security, Aalto University	Fall 2022
o Formal Languages and Finite Automata, University of Leeds	Spring 2020